All right, so today’s דף, daf, today’s דף daf is למ"ד ח'.
Lamed Chet. We started at the very bottom of למ"ד ח' עמוד
ב' Lamed Chet Amud Bet and it’s אמר ליה רב ירמיה לרב
זירא. Amar Lei Rav Yirmiya Le-Rav Zeira. Just three lines up. מתיב
רב יוסף בר שמואל. Masiv Rav Yosef Bar Shmuel. Okay, thank you.
מתיב, Masiv, second line of the widest line towards the end of
the line, מתיב רב יוסף בר שמואל. Masiv Rav Yosef Bar Shmuel.
So רב יוסף
בר שמואל
Rav
Yosef Bar Shmuel asks, this
is an ongoing discussion of whether cooked vegetables get a בורא פרי
האדמה Borei Pri Ha-Adama or not. Is it only when the vegetables
go from inedible to edible, or תוספות Tosafot points out maybe if
they're equivalently good when they're cooked, but would they even get a
בורא פרי האדמה Borei Pri Ha-Adama even if they're not as ideal
as they're cooked? Or you know, obviously there's some people want them
but they're generally not considered as ideal. So that's the question. So
within this,
מתיב רב
יוסף בר שמואל, Masiv Rav Yosef Bar Shmuel, so רב יוסף בר
שמואל Rav Yosef Bar Shmuel asks, ירקות שאדם יוצא בהן ידי חובתו
בפסח, Yerakos she-adam yotzei ba-hen yedei hovato ba-Pesach, right, if the vegetables
that you fulfill your פסח Pesach obligation for מרור, Maror,
יוצא בהן, yotzei ba-hen, you fulfill your obligation through them ובקלח שלהן,
u-be-kelach she-la-hen, their stalk, אבל לא כבושים, aval lo kevushim, not if
they are pickled, ולא שלוקין, ve-lo shelukin, not if they are like
double-boiled, ולא מבושלים, ve-lo mevushalim, and not if they’re just regularly cooked.
So only if you have them raw. אי סלקא דעתך במלתייהו קיימי,
I salka da'atach be-milsaihu kaimei, if you think that after being cooked
something is considered essentially to be in the same state, שלוקין אמאי
לא, shelukin amai lo, so why if you boil them or cook
them are they not good for פסח? Pesach? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, שאני התם דבעינן טעם מרור וליכא. shani hatam de-ba'inan ta'am
maror ve-leika.
There they are considered, you know, the vegetable, but they don't have
the right taste for מרור, Maror, so that's a secondary consideration.
How can it be the same vegetable if it loses its taste?
Well, things taste different depending on how you prepared them. So in
terms of the object, do we still consider it, thank you, to
be, you know, the same object? Yes. But it’s, you know, let's
say I don't know, let's say you put cinnamon on it or
something, you also wouldn't be יוצא. yotzei.
So its identity is its appearance and its structure and not its
taste.
Taste is not sufficient, let's put it that way, to or well,
actually I should say right,
the change of taste is not sufficient to say that it's no
longer the same thing. That is correct. So at least for ברכות
Brachos purpose. So that's the end of the discussion about cooked vegetables.
I should say that תוספות Tosafot does not know in the מסקנא.
maskana. It’s clear that if something is really pretty inedible raw, you
make a שהכל Shehakol raw and a בורא פרי האדמה Borei Pri
Ha-Adama once it’s cooked and edible. The question is what’s the מסקנא
maskana of the גמרא Gemara the opposite way? If it’s edible raw
and maybe even ideal raw but every now and then you cook
it. So תוספות Tosafot is inclined to say that only if it’s
the same or better when you cook it. But if cooking it
actually makes it worse, you know, less ideal for most people, then
you’d actually say a שהכל. Shehakol. But he quotes the רי"ף Rif
that says that you would actually make a בורא פרי האדמה. Borei
Pri Ha-Adama. In general, unless something is really considered to like be
transformed,
like I think most people probably I mean it’s a debate what
means better or worse, but for example most people I think eat
raw carrots, right? When we
cook carrots or
most people eat raw tomatoes, if you had boiled tomatoes you’d still
make a בורא פרי האדמה Borei Pri Ha-Adama on them. So as
long as it retains basically the shape. If it transforms the shape,
different considerations come up, yes. You had a question? No.
Yes, so because we were just discussing about that just at the
end of the שיעור, shiur, and garlic. The גמרא Gemara gave it
as an example, most people would probably be more likely to eat
it, you know, in a stir-fry or like, nobody’s munching on garlic.
Yeah, that’s different, no, no, no. That’s okay, I don't want to
get into the ultimate פסק psak of the גמרא Gemara but I
will say תוספות Tosafot asks that to some degree. Yes, you’ll eat
garlic cooked but not because you’ll eat the raw garlic, because you
want the stuff that’s cooked in. So that, you know, anyway it
was funny the example of garlic but תוספות Tosafot points out the
fact that you eat it with other things is really you're eating
the other things that are flavored by garlic, you're not eating it
raw.
I had a main dish stir-fried garlic sprouts, they were delicious.
Oh really? All right, yeah anyway, let's move on. So that's the
end of the discussion about cooked. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר ליה רב ירמיה לרב זירא, Amar Lei Rav Yirmiya Le-Rav
Zeira, so now we’re going back to some of the stories we
discussed or some of the מעשים. ma'asim. So רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiya
said to רב זירא, Rav Zeira, how could you have made a
ברכה bracha on that salted
olive, right, because we left off with he ate a salted object,
a salted olive, and that was similar to like a cooked vegetable.
It was seen as a similar. So the גמרא Gemara says how
could he have eaten that? כיון דשקליה לגרעיניה, keivan de-shaklei le-gar'inei,
he didn't eat the seed of it obviously, the pit of the
olive, so therefore בטליה לשיעורא, batlei shiura, so he didn't have an
olive worth, he didn't have a כזית ke-zayit worth of an olive.
So therefore, now why is that a question? So תוספות Tosafot very
importantly points out בטליה לשיעורא, batlei shiura,
the first line of
תוספות, Tosafot, היינו דוקא בברכה שלאחריו, hayinu davka be-bracha she-acharei, that you
need a שיעור, shiur, אבל ברכה שלפניו aval bracha she-lefanav even פחות
מכשיעור, pachus mi-keshiur, it’s forbidden to enjoy this world without a ברכה,
bracha, whether for אכילה achila or for שתיה shsiya etc. Okay, so
תוספות Tosafot makes it very clear that there's no שיעור shiur for
a ברכה bracha before, the שיעור shiur is for the ברכה bracha
afterwards. I will tell you an interesting question. So washing is a
different consideration. But the ברכה brakha beforehand is even if it's the
smallest amount. The ברכה brakha afterwards, that's where you need a כזית.
kezayit.
But if you're testing food when you're cooking it?
Yes, so that's a different question. That's a good question whether טעימה
teima is considered אכילה achila or not. A little, putting it on
the tip of your tongue. So there's a lot of opinions that
it's not and it doesn't need a ברכה. brakha. So that's a
good point. That might be different. Okay, so the question is how
did he make, and the story before said he made a final
ברכה. brakha. How did he make a final ברכה? brakha? He only
had one olive. Minus the pit is still not enough of an
olive. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, מי סברת
כזית גדול בעינן? mi savrat kezayit gadol beinan? What makes you think
we need a big כזית? kezayit? כזית בינוני בעינן, kezayit beinoni beinan,
we only need an average-sized olive.
וההיא דאייתו לקמיה דרבי יוחנן, ve-hahi d'aitu l'kamei d'rabbi yochanan, the olive
they brought Rabbi Yochanan, זית גדול הוה, zayit gadol hava, it was
a big one. So it was so big that אף על גב
דשקלוה לגרעיניה, af al gav d'shakluha l'garineia, even though they removed the
pit, פש ליה שיעורא, pash lei shiura, it still was a medium-sized
כזית. kezayit. A big כזית kezayit minus the pit equals a medium-sized
olive. And therefore דתנן, d'tnan, we taught in the משנה, mishna, זית
שאמרו, zayit she-amru, when they talk about the זית zayit for measuring
things, כזית, kezayit, when someone says כזית, kezayit, but it's like a
זית, zayit, the size of an olive. So what type of an
olive? לא קטן ולא גדול, lo katan v'lo gadol, not a small
olive, not a big olive, אלא בינוני, ela beinoni, an average olive.
Okay?
We're talking about removing its pit, right? Suggests that size here means
weight. No, volume. But the size doesn't change.
Yeah, but no, even when we say volume, we mean volume minus
the air. Meaning that's a good point. The size is always assumed
to be volume. Okay, yes, but if I have something like something
hollowed out, right, and it's just the outer shell, then we don't
say that's the requisite size. The size is like minus the air
space. That's the assumption. You're right, it's never said explicitly, but it's
pretty implicit here. That leads to all these discussions about like bread,
how much bread do you need for a כזית, kezayit, or מצה
matzah when people go crazy, how much you have to squish it.
Right. I mean, what does it mean you remove the air? Right,
exactly. Here obviously there's a whole hollow to it. So that the
fact that the hollow of the olive doesn't count makes sense. But
if something is fluffy that you have to squish it, normally you
probably don't. Okay, but there is that discussion about bread. Okay, so
the כזית kezayit is not small and not big. Anyway, it's very
clear because there's I think even a תוספתא, tosefta, other sources, like
tannaitic sources that discuss how you measure these things and basically talk
about water displacement. So though they, it was interesting they knew about
water displacement and B, it was clear that they're talking about volume.
Okay, so it says not small, not big,
אלא בינוני, ela beinoni, just right, medium-sized. וזהו אגורי. ve-zehu aguri. This
is the אגורי aguri olive. ואמר רבי אבהו, ve-amar rabbi abbahu, and
רבי אבהו rabbi abbahu said, לא אגורי שמו, lo aguri shemo, not
אגורי aguri is its name, אלא אברוטי שמו. ela avruti shemo. Its
name is the אברוטי avruti olive. ואמרי לה
סמרוסי שמו, ve-amrei lah samrusi shemo, some say its name is the
סמרוסי samrusi olive. ואמאי קרי ליה אגורי, ve-amai karei lei aguri, why
is it called the אגורי aguri olive? ששמנו אגור בתוכו. she-shamno agur
betokho. It's very juicy and the oil is like contained within it.
So it's a particular type of an olive, that is your average
olive size. I'll say that there's a very interesting article by Natan
Slifkin that deals with the changing size of the olive and the
different olives that the ראשונים rishonim had from the Mediterranean olives and
how that led to all these questions about why our olive size
is much bigger than it really was in the time of the
גמרא gemara because they were dealing with different olives. So it's a
good article, I would advise you to look at that. I will
say it is quite funny, I remember once that I actually was
eating olives and I said, oh I wonder if I have enough
for ברכה אחרונה, brakha achrona, I wonder if there was a כזית
kezayit there. Wait, wait, wait, exactly the case. So sometimes these שיעורים
shiurim come totally detached from reality and also become disproportionate to what
they were in the time of the גמרא. gemara. So here the
גמרא gemara actually said an olive should be an olive's worth, but
then we have the problem of the pit. Okay, so now the
גמרא gemara continues and says like
this: לימא כתנאי. leima k'tannai. Maybe this issue is a debate of
תנאים tannaim back to the question about cooked vegetables.
דהנהו תרי תלמידי דהוו יתבי קמיה דבר קפרא. d'hanhu terei talmidei d'havu
yatvei kamei d'bar kappara. There were two students that were sitting in
the presence of
בר קפרא. bar kappara. הביאו לפניו, hevi'u lefanav, they brought to בר
קפרא, bar kappara, כרוב, kruv, a cabbage, cooked cabbage presumably, ודורמסקין, ve-durmaskin,
and דורמסקין, durmaskin, I'll get to that in a minute, ופרגיות, ve-pargyot,
and like young cooked birds, pigeons or something of that nature. Now
what's this דורמסקין? durmaskin? If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says,
well I guess the four lines down in the רש"י Rashi he
says, or three lines down he says, אבל כאן פירש aval kan
peireish prunes. You see that? וכן שמעתי אני כאן ובכמה ve-khein shamati
ani kan u-ve-khama prunes. So if you take a look at the
שטיינזלץ, Steinsaltz, he's got these nice damson plums, which are those small
little black nice little picture there. The problem רש"י Rashi says to
read it that way is it's going to be clear from the
גמרא gemara that the ברכה brakha is אדמה. adama. And not clear
until now we've been dealing even if things are cooked
between אדמה Adamah and שהכל, Shehakol, presumably it'd also be העץ HaEtz
and שהכל Shehakol if it's cooked and it goes down a ברכה.
beracha. Can something go down from העץ HaEtz to אדמה Adamah is
not so clear. So רש״י Rashi would rather assume this is and
תוספות Tosafot it's a type of a cabbage because this גמרא Gemara
is going to assume that the ברכה beracha on it was a
would naturally be אדמה Adamah and it's cooked so maybe it's שהכל.
Shehakol.
So what happened next?
Because
nothing that's just what happened. Okay. So you had let's say for
argument's sake you had these cooked vegetables and
some nice chicken some nice pigeon there in front of you. So
thus Bar Kapra ברשות אחד מהן לברך. birshut echad mehen l'vareich. He
said to one of the students here you make the ברכה. beracha.
קפץ ובירך על הפרגיות kafatz u'veirach al ha'pargiyot so he jumped forward
and he made the ברכה beracha on the poultry. ליגלג עליו חבירו
ligleig alav chaveiro so the other one was mocking him. So you
make a ברכה beracha on the chicken you make a ברכה beracha
on the fruit first or the cabbage first. So איקפד ikpad Bar
Kapra so בר קפרא bar Kapra got angry. אמר לא על המברך
אני כועס amar lo al ha'mevareich ani ko'eis I'm not angry on
the one who made the ברכה beracha אלא על המלגלג אני כועס
ela al ha'melagleig ani ko'eis I'm angry at the one that mocked
him. אם חברך דומה כמי שלא טעם טעם בשר מעולם im chavarcha
domeh k'mi she'lo ta'am ta'am basar mei'olam he's not exactly complimentary if
your friend looked like somebody who's starving never had any meat before
he was very eager to have this delicious pigeon or whatever it
was. אתה למה ליגלגת atah lamah liglagta why did you feel you
had to mock him. Okay what he did maybe wasn't ideal but
what made you think you were right to mock him. חזר ואמר
chazar v'amar then he rethought it and he said you know what
לא על המלגלג אני כועס lo al ha'melagleig ani ko'eis I'm not
angry on the one who mocked him אלא על המברך אני כועס
ela al ha'mevareich ani ko'eis I'm angry at the one who made
the ברכה beracha why. ואמר אם חכמה אין כאן v'amar im chochmah
ein kan even if there's no wisdom in
you זקנה אין כאן ziknah ein kan so is there no are
there no elderly people in the room are there no sages in
the room. Like even if you don't know what to do you
could have asked me. So why did he not know what to
do what he do wrong that he made a ברכה beracha on
שהכל Shehakol before a ברכה beracha of אדמה Adamah and now we're
going to get into this discussion of priority of ברכות berachot that
if you have multiple foods in front of you you make the
ones with the more specific ברכה beracha before the ones with the
more general ברכה beracha העץ HaEtz comes before אדמה Adamah אדמה Adamah
comes before שהכל Shehakol and so on.
Right and we saw earlier with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva the same
לשון lashon of קפץ ובירך. kafatz u'veirach. Right and there we thought
maybe he was trying to say quickly so that רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel didn't hear you know he had a chance to say what
he thought to say.
Right right there there was a debate of the ברכה beracha right
here it seems like it's now a standard idiomatic phrase. Right for
responding with alacrity without any judgment or valence.
Exactly exactly I agree. It's not just you're trying to get it
in before you could be interrupted.
Right and no negative valence.
Right or well the negative valence might be here like the אם
חכמה אין כאן זקנה אין כאן im chochmah ein kan ziknah ein
kan you should have consulted me you you know so there's still
this sense as like you rushed forward.
As a literary expression it might be when it says קפץ ובירך
kafatz u'veirach we should anticipate there's going to be some
reaction going to be something that will happen.
That is a nice way of saying absolutely the fact that you
jumped forward means yeah something here is amiss. Okay so right so
now the גמרא Gemara says תנא ושניהם לא הוציאו שנתן tana u'shneihem
lo hotziu shenatam those two students neither of them lived out the
year which means that the because of בר קפרא's bar Kapra's sort
of critical responses they both died within the year which then so
don't take yeah of course it's obviously disturbing because from our perspective
it's like whatever they did why was it so bad you know
if you said who here did the worst thing if somebody's curse
makes them die within the year for this type of an overstep.
So you know the מהרש״א Maharsha tries to tie it into another
גמרא Gemara that speaks about the somebody that we've seen before מורה
הלכה בפני רבו moreh halacha bifnei rabbo you know it's like חייב
מיתה chayav misah so in a sense they were מורה הלכה בפני
רבו moreh halacha bifnei rabbo the one who made the you know
both of them were essentially voicing an opinion either by the ברכה
beracha they made or by the mocking of what the הלכה halacha
should be. So I know so anyways problem is the first whatever
anyway the first one because he did the wrong thing and the
second one because if there's need in correction I should be the
one to correct him. So it's obviously a problematic story yes. And
the word תנא tana
we taught in a ברייתא Baraisa it's just ושניהם לא הוציאו. u'shneihem
lo hotziu.
Because presumably that's a separate you're right because presumably that's a separate
ברייתא Baraisa like that's a postscript not in this version of the
story that's a good point as well right it's a later postscript
from a different source that's a good point too right it did
not have to be part of the original story yes.
Aren't we forbidden to say by השם Hashem that to ascribe you
know like the death
of someone to.
It's not ascribing it's just suggesting it's you know just. It says
here's what happened and he said this oh and by the way
they both died within the year you want to draw conclusions that's
up to you.
What?
No I think that's that's pure semantics the fact of the matter
is they knew by saying that
that people would draw conclusions.
Absolutely. Right, right. Just a subtle, more subtle...
yeah. Look, the whole question about how do we sort of understand
how God is acting and you know and... it's an extremely, you
know, a...
I would say conflicted one in the גמרא, Gemara, maybe conflicted is
the wrong word. I'll give you for example, the fact the גמרא
Gemara says that on the one hand it says as we learned
in the beginning of ברכות, Berachos, if you see bad things happening
to you, you should be reflecting what have I done to deserve
this and it should be a spur to do תשובה, Teshuva, and
on the other hand a very famous גמרא Gemara says that if
somebody suffered a loss and you say to them like, oh this
must have happened because of your sins, that this is, you know,
you're transgressing the biblical prohibition of afflicting somebody with your words. So
it's one thing if you use it for yourself as a means
of self-introspection and whatever, and as another thing if you tell somebody
else that this is how God is acting. So you know, anyway,
let's that's purely just pointing my argument. Yeah, let's acknowledge that this
is difficult, this fact about them dying. So back though to the
halachic discussion here. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי לאו
בהא קמיפלגי? Mai lav be-ha ka mipalgi?
So the גמרא Gemara turns these two students who obviously were, you
know, a little impetuous and misbehaving in one way or another, into
a halachic debate. Let's say this is what they're debating about. דמברך
סבר שלקות ופרגיות שהכל נהיה
בדברו. De-mevarech savar shelakos u-fargiyos she-hakol nihiya bi-dvaro. Just look, pigeon and
cooked vegetables, שהכל. she-hakol. הלכך חביב
עדיף, Hilkach chaviv adif, I'll make the ברכה bracha on the one
that I am more interested in, that's more dear to me, I'd
rather have the pigeon. ומלגלג סבר, U-melaglech savar, the mocker thought, שלקות
בורא פרי האדמה, shelakos borei pri ha-adama, even if they're cooked you
make a בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri ha-adama. פרגיות, Pargiyos, and these
פרגיות pargiyos שהכל נהיה בדברו she-hakol nihiya bi-dvaro is some type of
poultry, you make
שהכל. she-hakol. והלכך פרט עדיף, Ve-hilkach perat adif, it's better to make
the more specific ברכה. bracha. גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no, דכולי
עלמא שלקות ופרגיות שהכל נהיה בדברו. de-kulei alma shelakos u-fargiyos she-hakol nihiya
bi-dvaro. We could say like that they all would agree that cooked
vegetables if it goes down, let's say minimally, is a שהכל she-hakol
and everything here was a שהכל. she-hakol. הכא בהאי סברא קמיפלגי. Hacha
be-hai sevara ka mipalgi.
Here's what they were debating. מר סבר חביב עדיף. Mar savar chaviv
adif.
If they're both שהכל, she-hakol, which one do you make a ברכה
bracha on? Equal ברכות. brachos. One says the one that's more dear
to you, that you're more eager to be eating. ומר סבר כרוב
עדיף. U-mar savar krov adif.
No, the cabbage is better even if you like the pigeon more,
why? דזיין, di-zayin,
because it satiates more. So if one is more of a filler
and one is more of a staple, and the other is more
of a delicacy, so even if the delicacy is more dear to
you, you make the ברכה bracha first on the one that more
satiates, which is nice, because you know, it speaks to the idea
in a way, you know, it's interesting this whole idea about making
the more specific before the more general. And
but in particular in this application, you know, it's sort of like
the issue of even there when you're dealing with your desire and
your appetite and your eating and so on, to be, you know,
acknowledge, I mean the whole idea of ברכות brachos is to sort
of sanctify the act of eating and it's not all about satisfying
your lusts etc. So here to be saying actually you prioritize something
that's more of a staple than something that's more of a delicacy,
you know, there's a nice sort of message to that in the
context
of eating here and of something that's about satisfying your desires. So
let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara has a lot to say
about this.
They're not saying just say שהכל she-hakol and cover everything.
No, they actually
specifically you should say the right blessing.
Well, there's two issues. One is for specificity you say the right,
you say the more narrow one first, but when they are of
equal you know sort of ברכה, bracha, then there's a question of
how do you prioritize? Now when you are going to pick the
one you say first, if it's a שהכל, she-hakol, you'll have in
mind everything else, so you will be מוציא motzi the other things,
but there's still a question of which one you're making the ברכה
bracha on. Okay, so that is correct. Have a look by the
way about that issue about making the ברכה bracha on something. So
if you look at תוספות נתן בר קפרא רשות לאחד מהן לברך.
Tosafos nasan bar kappar reshus le-echad me-hen levarech. תוספות Tosafos says ונראה
דמאי בברכה שלפניו, ve-nireh de-mai bi-bracha she-lifanav, which is clear because the
whole question is שהכל בורא פרי האדמה. she-hakol borei pri ha-adama. דבשל
אחר אפילו הכי דאין מזמנינן על הפירות, de-bi-shel achar af-pi-hen de-ein me-zamninan
al ha-peiros, because if it's the ברכה bracha afterwards, right, which is
בורא נפשות borei nefashos etc., so you don't do a זימון zimmun
afterwards. One person doesn't make a ברכה bracha for other people afterwards.
But then he says ומיירי
בהסיבה, u-mairi be-heseiba, that they have done הסיבה. heseiba.
They're reclining and essentially they're eating together as a group. And as
a... אנו אין לנו שום הסיבה אלא על הפת וכן צריך לברך
כל אחד ואחד על דבר הן בפירות הן ביין. anu ein lanu
shum heseiba ela al ha-pas ve-chen tzarich levarech kol echad ve-echad al
davar hem be-peiros hem be-yayin. Everybody makes their own ברכה, bracha, somebody
doesn't make a ברכה bracha for someone else. So the reason I
read this is because this will get us to the issues of
the next פרק, perek, which is when can you be מוציא motzi
somebody else in a ברכת הנהנין birkas ha-nehenin and in a final
ברכה bracha in a ברכת המזון? birkat ha-mazon? We all know the
institution of זימון. zimmun. זימון zimmun was normally not just three lines
you say in the beginning, but it really was somebody did the
ברכה bracha for the whole group, the ברכת המזון birkat ha-mazon for
the whole group. And that's why the question is whether there's זימון
בפירות, zimmun be-peiros, when can you define something as a corporate group
that one person can represent them and make the ברכה, bracha, and
the general assumption is only when they're having bread and they're having
a meal. together, a real fixed meal. So that's the similar question
of can you make a ברכה Bracha for somebody else beforehand, since
this is very particular about your benefit, your being, you experiencing this
pleasure, maybe it requires your personal ברכה. Bracha. So what תוספות Tosafot
is saying is, here where רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or whoever was
one of these students was making בר קפרא Bar Kappara for the
others, it was because they were all having a הסיבה, Haseiba, it
was a type of a meal that was experienced as a group
and הסיבה Haseiba was a meaningful experience. It wasn't just we all
decided to sit down, הסיבה Haseiba was culturally a meaningful experience of
eating together. And therefore, you could have one making the ברכה Bracha
for others. But when really you don't have that sort of institution
of הסיבה, Haseiba, that cultural phenomenon, then fundamentally we're considered to be
eating our individual pleasure and we make our own ברכות. Brachot. So
that is very important conceptually in the idea of when you're a
unit, when you're not a unit, when one person can make a
ברכה Bracha for others. It's not like מצוות Mitzvot where we say
I can make a ברכה Bracha for you. Here it's very much
about the pleasure that you personally are experiencing. Okay,
so we will talk about that as we go on. There are
cases בדיעבד Bedi'avad like for example, you don't know if you've made
a ברכה, Bracha, this or that, where I can make a ברכה
Bracha for you if I also am נהנה, Nehene, like for example
think about the rabbi under the חופה. Chuppah. He says בורא פרי
הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen and then he gives to the חתן Chatan
and the כלה. Kallah. Sometimes the problem is that the rabbi doesn't
drink from the wine. So they tell the trick they tell you
is you sort of shake the cup a little, you get a
little on your finger and then you wet your finger as you're
handing it over. But actually the הלכה Halakha is that if you
do make a ברכת הנהנין Birkat Hanehenin and you are נהנה, Nehene,
you can be מוציא Motzi somebody else, but תוספות Tosafot says לכתחילה
Lechatchila not. לכתחילה Lechatchila each person should be making their own
ברכת הנהנין.
Birkat Hanehenin. That'd be an argument for everybody making their own קידוש.
Kiddush.
Yeah, but קידוש Kiddush is different because there קידוש, Kiddush, the בורא
פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen of קידוש Kiddush is more part of
the ברכת הקידוש Birkat HaKiddush and the גמרא Gemara discusses that explicitly,
so that has a different quality and that's also partly the answer
to Micah, which is although the ברכת בורא פרי הגפן Birkat Borei
Pri HaGafen by ברכת אירוסין Birkat Erusin was introduced after the גמרא,
Gemara, it sort of traditionally has become essentially part of the ברכת
אירוסין Birkat Erusin like קידוש Kiddush and ברכת המזון. Birkat HaMazon.
Yeah, less in ברכת הנהנין. Birkat HaNehenin.
That means that מצוות Mitzvot are intrinsically corporate in their dimension. Although
there is an idea,
I'm not sure I'd say that's one way of saying it. Another
way of saying it
is that things that are about ברכות Brachot about הנאה, Hana'ah,
it's extremely personal, the type of sense of the pleasure that I
got, whereas the מצוה Mitzvah is more sort of something a little
bit more participation in.
It's participation in, right, right.
But I'm not saying that every time I do a מצוה Mitzvah
we're all doing it as כלל ישראל, Kelal Yisrael, but it's less
of a personal ברכה, Bracha, so therefore I can piggyback on somebody
else. So now that's this issue about what ברכה Bracha they made.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, said רב זירא, Rav Zeira,
כי הוינא בי רב הונא, Ki havina bei Rav Huna, when I
was in the house of רב הונא, Rav Huna, אמר לן, Amar
lan, he said to us, הני גרגלידי דליפתא, Hanei gargelidi de'lifta, the
heads of turnips,
פרמינהו פרמא רבא, Parmuneihu parma rabba, if you cut them into big
chunks, בורא פרי האדמה, Borei Pri HaAdamah, you make בורא פרי האדמה.
Borei Pri HaAdamah. פרמא זוטא, Parma zuta, if you mince them into
tiny little pieces, שהכל נהיה בדברו, Shehakol Nihiya Bidvaro, then you say
שהכל. Shehakol. Presumably because it's נשתנה, Nishtanah, it doesn't look so much
like a turnip anymore, looks like little white pieces. Okay, וכי אתם
בי רב יהודה, Vechi asam bei Rav Yehudah, when we came to
רב יהודה, Rav Yehudah, אמר לן, Amar lan, he said to us,
אידי ואידי בורא פרי האדמה. Idi ve'idi Borei Pri HaAdamah. You make
בורא פרי האדמה Borei Pri HaAdamah on both. ודפרמינהו טפי, Vedeparminu tfei,
but that's only if you mince them very well, כי היכי דנמתיק
טעמיה, Ki heichi de'namtik ta'amei, so that it makes it sweeter, it
makes it better. So it's נשתנה, Nishtanah, it's changed, but it's נשתנה
למעליותא, Nishtanah le'meilyusa, it actually is better, certainly it's not worse. And
this becomes, if you remember, the principle we had starting a few
days ago, that when things have a changed form, if they have
a changed form and they're seen as less ideal, it becomes a
שהכל. Shehakol. If it's equivalent, certainly if it's better, it's בורא פרי
האדמה, Borei Pri HaAdamah, and that's what he is saying. If you
mince them that well, even if it doesn't look so much like
a turnip, it's still בורא פרי האדמה. Borei Pri HaAdamah.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב אשי, Amar
Rav Ashi, said רב אשי, Rav Ashi, כי הוינא בי רב כהנא,
Ki havina bei Rav Kahana, when I was in the house of
רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, אמר לן, Amar lan, he said to us,
תבשילא דסילקא דלא משדי ביה קמחא, Tavshila de'silka de'la mashu bei kimcha,
if you have a stew of סילקא Silka of beets that you
have not had a lot of flour in, בורא פרי האדמה, Borei
Pri HaAdamah, then you say בורא פרי האדמה. Borei פרי האדמה. דליפתא,
De'lifta, but if you have turnip stew, דמשדי ביה קמחא טפי, De'mashu
bei kimcha tfei, where the practice is to put a lot of
flour in it, בורא מיני מזונות, Borei Minei Mezonot, you make a
בורא מיני מזונות. Borei Minei Mezonot. So we've had something like this
before as well, if there's a lot of flour and the flour
is the עיקר, Ikkar, בורא מיני מזונות. Borei Minei Mezonot. והדר אמר,
Vahadar amar, but
then he reversed himself and he said, אידי ואידי בורא פרי האדמה.
Idi ve'idi Borei Pri HaAdamah. You know what, both are בורא פרי
האדמה. Borei Pri HaAdamah. Why? והאי דשדי ביה קמחא טפי, Vehai deshavi
bei kimcha tfei, why do they put so much flour in this
turnip stew? לדבוקי בעלמא עביד ליה, Ledevukei be'alma avidlei, only for using
it as a sticking
agent, to give the soup a little thickness, but it's not really
about the flour. And this becomes the very important principle as I
told you. before, while in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* there's an idea
that עיקר וטפל *ikkar v'tafel* applies equally to מזונות mezonos, *mezonot* and
even to bread, that if bread is טפל *tafel* to herring, you
would make a ברכה bracha *bracha* on the herring and not on
the bread. In the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it becomes anytime you have
מזונות Mezonos, *mezonot*, מזונות *mezonot* always wins in some type of a
mixture with the one exception when it's doing an act of לדבוקי
*lidvukei*, you know, to sort of make things just like as a
sticking agent. The question is- well, here it's thickening, but also you
could imagine like, you know, sometimes you put the dough there in
order to like get the other stuff to clump together. The problem
is what exactly are the parameters of לדבוקי *lidvukei*? The example I
gave- give is like, you know, schnitzel, who- you know, where you-
you know, put in flour. No, it's not לדבוקי *lidvukei*, but I
would like to see the person who's going to make a בורא
מיני מזונות *borei minei mezonot* on schnitzel. So- you know, so the
question is- so some explain it the other way. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*
says, you know, maybe it's that you have to be putting it
there for the purpose of לסעוד *liso'od*, to fill you up, you
know, and that's obviously what a major thing, you know, the dough
would do and that flour would do, it would be there to
sort of fill you. If it's serving the purpose and that I
think is how we tend to- our general approach. If it's doing
some secondary culinary thing, to add crunch, you know, to give it
a type of a coating or whatever, generally tend to say that
you don't make a מזונות *mezonot*. If it's coming there to actually
be part of the sort of, you know, the fill of what
you're eating, then we do. You know, but there's always these ambiguous
cases, like there's, you know, an apple crunch, right? Which it's like
there's a lot of that crunchy stuff, so it's there for crunch,
but it's also there to add filler, you know, it's- it's there
to add- be part of the substance. So if you take a
look of course what do you do? So if you take- so
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, you know, says not this תוספות Tosafos. *Tosafot*, other
תוספותים *Tosafotim*, he constantly is quoting the מהרם מרוטנבורג Maharam mi'Rothenburg *Maharam
m'Rothenburg*. I meant to say this before, I've told you earlier תוספותים
*Tosafotim* that say, you know what? Just make a המוציא Hamotzi. *Hamotzi*,
have it in the middle of the meal so you don't- don't
get out of a problem which is like well how a lot
of people treat all הלכות hilchos ברכות brachos, *hilchot brachot*. We're actually
going to see something like that coming up in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. But as to when those were saying it that I was
suspecting that that was from the מהרם מרוטנבורג *Maharam m'Rothenburg* because that
is- מהרם מרוטנבורג *Maharam m'Rothenburg* for example is the one that found
a piece of hard cheese in his teeth many hours after having
eaten cheese and decided that we have to wait six hours after
eating hard cheese. So the מהרם מרוטנבורג *Maharam m'Rothenburg* had this- you
know, was this whole- this whole idea 'play it safe' and be
מחמיר *machmir* was very much part of his approach to things and
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* one of these תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* quotes explicitly the
מהרם *Maharam* who says, you know, have it in the meal so
you don't have to worry about which ברכה bracha *bracha* to make.
So that's sort of a refrain here in תוספות Tosfos. *Tosafot*. The
מהרם מרוטנבורג *Maharam m'Rothenburg* was 13th century, so it's a later תוספות
Tosfos *Tosafot* here, but it's clearly a student of the מהרם *Maharam*.
Anyway, but this becomes- there are some cases where it's hard to
exactly know whether it's מזונות *mezonot* or not.
Yeah, we discussed this the other day, I mean, and if- if
I recall correctly, שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* said, you know, things depend
on whether it's set or not and whether it's cooked or not.
Oh, that's the whole thing with breadcrumbs and whatever.
Yeah, but the schnitzel is a breadcrumbs, isn't it?
No, some do it in flour. You know, if you did it
in breadcrumbs, you're right, that would be a different question. But if
you some- some sort of pat it with like flounder, you know,
you put flour on it and so on. Okay, so let's take
a look. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. Okay. אמר רב חסדא
*Amar Rav Chisda*, said רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*, תבשיל של תרדין *tavshil
shel tardin*, תרדין *tardin*, I guess, a beet stew... spinach? Spinach is
how it translates תרדין *tardin*. That is so interesting. Beet. Really? It's
beet. Beet. Yeah, who- who says spinach? הירק *Hayerek* is the Hebrew
word for spinach. Okay, as far- in Aramaic רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, it's
רש"י *Rashi* and whatever
classic translators say it's beet and it's actually make it identical with
another word of beet.
סלקא *silka* is right.
So סלקא *silka* and תרדין *tardin*
are both- רש"י
*Rashi* identifies them and they're both presumably beet. Okay. תבשיל של תרדין
יפה ללב *Tavshil shel tardin yafe lalev* is good for the heart,
וטוב לעיניים
*v'tov l'einayim*, good for the eyes, וכל שכן לבני מעיים *v'chol
shekein l'vnei mei'ayim*, it's certainly good for the intestines, cleans out the
intestines. אמר אביי *Amar Abaye*, והוא דיתיב אביתפי *v'hu d'yativ a'beitafi*, that's
only if you're while the stew is- or the soup is cooking,
you're sitting right there by the pot, והוי תוכתוך *v'havi tuch tuch*,
and the pot is you know sort of like it's bubbling and
it's sort of against the lid of the pot so it's making
a tuk tuk tuk sound as it's cooking. You have to I
guess sit there to make sure that it's like bubbling well or
something. Okay, ומיא דלפתא *u'maya d'lifta*, now turnip water, כליפתא *k'lifta*. I
skipped a line. אמר רב פפא Rav Pappa *Amar Rav Papa*, said
רב פפא *Rav Papa*, פשיטא לי *peshita li*, it's obvious to me,
מיא דסלקא כסלקא *maya d'silka k'silka*, beet water, water cooked with beets
is like beet and you make a בורא פרי האדמה borei pri
ha'adama *borei pri ha'adama*. ומיא דלפתא *u'maya d'lifta*, turnip water, כליפתא *k'lifta*,
is like turnips and you make- and you also make a בורא
פרי האדמה ha'adamah *borei pri ha'adama*. Now, if you take a look
at תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*, תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* says, מיא דסלקא כסלקא *maya
d'silka k'silka*, says תוספות Tosfos. *Tosafot*, מברכין עליו בורא פרי האדמה *mevarchin
alav borei pri ha'adama*, אף על פי שאין בו אלא מים וטעם
הירק *af al pi she'ein bo ela mayim v'ta'am hayerek*, even though
it's only water and the taste of the vegetable, מברך עליהם כשמברך
על הירק *mevarech aleihem k'shemevarech al hayerek*, אף על גב דאמרינן לעיל
דמי פירות זיעה בעלמא zei'ah be'alma, הוא *af al gav d'amrinan l'eil
d'mei peirot zei'a b'alma hu*, orange juice you make a שהכל shehakol
*shehakol*, so יש לחלק *yesh l'chalek*, you can distinguish. I don't know
how to distinguish. If you have the actual essence of the orange
turned into juice you make a שהכל shehakol *shehakol*, you know, even
accepting that at that time it was considered unusual, whereas... why would
you make a בורא פרי האדמה on this? You would have to
say that it was so unusual to be drinking the juice, fruit
juices, that it was, you know, not considered to be a natural
use of it at all and it would be שהכל shehakol. not
because it wasn't in its original state, it was just so unnatural,
and that this because it was a natural way of getting benefit
from vegetables, you would still make a בורא פרי האדמה even though
it's a tremendous חידוש, chiddush, even though there's only the taste that's
being imparted, none of the essence, that's just like a transformed essence,
it's only the taste. There's huge debates about the halachic status of
this type of thing, of liquids that have been infused with taste,
like particularly around פסח, Pesach, where you know which is alcohol, right,
which is the, you know, the getting the whatever the, you know,
the flavor from the grain. So some obviously say it's חמץ גמור
chametz gamur and the other extreme some say it's totally מותר, mutar,
זיעה בעלמא, you know, so it's like, you know, this question here
of the liquids that are cooked with these things and what status
it has is a wide range and תוספות Tosfos himself acknowledges the
question. Is תוספות tosfos working with a concept of טעם כעיקר? ta'am
k'ikar? Well, so that's a possibility. טעם כעיקר ta'am k'ikar would really
be true in an area of like איסורין, issurin, but for ברכות,
Brachos I mean so much of the stuff here that loses its
ברכה bracha. and you go down to שהכל shehakol, is the essence
of orange surely has the taste of oranges in it, so it's
not sufficient to have טעם, ta'am, so you have to seek the
difference somewhere else. Yeah. I can't believe that this should be a
discussion for something like beer. Beer is 5,000, beer made from barley
is 5,000 years old. Right. This should have been decided a long
time ago. You mean because beer, what what ברכה bracha you make?
No, for פסח. Pesach. Oh, for פסח. Pesach. The גמרא Gemara mostly
you hear about mead, you don't hear about grain alcohol in the
גמרא Gemara that much. So I don't know, I'm not sure. We
have a beer recipe from ancient Babylonia from 5,000 years ago. Okay,
alright, so I don't know. The גמרא Gemara you mostly hear about
mead. Okay, anyway, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So
that becomes a very important question about, you know, liquids that have
taste of the vegetable or of the thing. Maybe also is it,
you know, from the משנה Mishna: it would imply since they differentiated
between wine that you make a בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen
and anything else, as we mentioned earlier, we make a שהכל. shehakol
I understand, but yeah, but the גמרא Gemara right moves away from
that. So now the גמרא Gemara says, בעי רב פפא, Ba'ei Rav
Pappa, so said, I'm sorry, ומייא דכולהו שלקי ככולהו שלקי, u'maya d'kuleihu
shalki k'kuleihu shalki, the water coming from any cooked vegetable is like
the vegetable, presumably would retain the ברכה. bracha בעי רב פפא, Ba'ei
Rav Pappa, so now רב פפא said, that I take for granted,
here's my question, מייא דשבתא מאי, maya d'shivsa mai, how about water
that you cooked in it שבתא shivsa which I think is what,
dill? Dill, spice. Dill, some type of a spice, dill. What's the
story? What's the question? למתוקי טעמא עבדי, l'metukei ta'ama avdi, do you
put the dill in to add flavor and then it would get
the ברכה bracha of אדמה? adama? It's like wild, right, to think
that you're cooking water, you're adding some flavoring, you make the ברכה
bracha, of אדמה, adama, anyway, או לעבורי זוהמא עבדי o l'avurei zuhama
avdi or it's only there to remove some of the foam or
some of the maybe bad taste but not actually to give a
good taste. So and what's the story? תא שמע, ta shma, come
in here, you want to drink this water, that's the case? I
guess, it sounds like it, that you'd be drinking the water straight.
I mean I don't know why else, I mean if it's other
things mixed into it, then it should be about the other things.
So לעבורי זוהמא l'avurei zuhama means you want your water to taste
better? I guess. I mean no, למתוקי l'metukei is you want it
to taste better. לעבורי זוהמא l'avurei zuhama somehow to remove a bad
taste. Okay. Herbal tea, coffee? Is that the same? Yeah, that's a
good actually that's an excellent example. If you're making tea, according to
this you would make a העץ ha'eitz or something or אדמה, adama,
I mean tea leaves come from a tree, right? Right, so what's
לעבורי זוהמא? l'avurei zuhama? Anyway, לעבורי זוהמא l'avurei zuhama somehow to remove
the bad taste, okay. I don't know, you're right, Michael, I agree.
If it's a stew, then I don't know why we're just talking
about the dill, there's other things presumably in this stew. But if
it's plain water, it doesn't make so much sense. Broth? Broth, but
what's else in it? Chicken? I mean nothing, so it's just a
broth. Everything's been removed, just a broth. But then why is the
only question the dill? What about all the other stuff that was
in it? All right. תא שמע, ta shma, come in here, השבת
משנתנה טעם בקדירה אין בה משום תרומה, hashives mishenasna ta'am bakdeira ein
ba mishum terumah, if you put the dill in the pot, once
it's changed the taste of the pot, then it's lost its own
taste and therefore the actual dill itself is no longer תרומה terumah
because it's all of its essence has gone out into the pot.
ואינה מטמאה טומאת אוכלין, v'eina mitama tumas ochalin, it's no longer food,
all of its essence has gone out. So why is that relevant
for us? שמע מינה למתוקי טעמא עבדי ליה, shma mina l'metukei ta'ama
avdi lei, it says it's changed the taste, it's added its taste
to the pot, so clearly it's being put in to add a
taste. שמע מינה. shma mina. And therefore once you accept this idea
that you make a שהכל, shehakol excuse me, that you make the
same ברכה bracha on the water that has the taste of other
vegetables in it, you would do the same here. I should, by
the way, point out because it gets to all this question about,
right, why we continue to make a שהכל Shehakol. on orange juice
if it's planted for that, and you know, coffee and all those
things. The idea that for drinks you always make a שהכל Shehakol.
is actually something quoted in an earlier תוספות. tosfos I don't know
if Michael mentioned it the other day, but actually תוספות tosfos on...
the תוספות tosfos on האי דובשא Hai Dubsha I should mention this
on מ"ח ע"א. Mem-Ches Amud Aleph. He deals with the issue about
mead, right, because mead is similar in something that comes from, from,
whatever it was, dates, honey, well, date honey I think, says תוספות.
tosfos So he says in the middle of that תוספות tosfos says
ושיכרא דידן v'shichra didan although there is despite the fact that it
has the essence of the date in it, although, ושיכרא דידן, v'shichra
didan, no, actually he's talking, excuse me, not mead, mead is, I'm
sorry, his ושיכרא דידן v'shichra didan means beer, excuse me. So he
says, how about our beer? We don't say מזונות, אלא שהכל. ela
shehakol. ואפילו רב ושמואל דאמרי כל שיש בו מחמשת המינים מברכין עליו
בורא מיני מזונות, v'afillu Rav u'Shmuel d'amri kol sheyesh bo m'chameshes haminim
m'varchin alav borei minei mezonos, הכא לא הוי ממש שעורים. hacha lo
havei mamash se'orim. It doesn't have real barley in it, it just
has the taste of the barley. It seems to be exactly against
the גמרא Gemara we just learned, right? ואין שיכרא אלא טעמא בעלמא.
v'ein shichra ela ta'ama b'alma. So this beer is only the taste
of the barley. ועוד משום דחזי לאחריני פת, v'od mishum d'chazi l'achrinei
pas, you could do other things with it, you could make it
into bread. ועוד בשתיה אומר שהכל. v'od b'shtiya omer shehakol. Maybe you're
drinking something you say שהכל. Shehakol? This is something the גמרא gemara
at all we have completely internalized is that other than wine, if
your drink is a שהכל. shehakol So you already have תוספות Tosafot
dealing with its our issue of orange juice is תוספות's Tosafot issue
of beer. Why are we only saying say מזונות, say אדמה, Adama,
don't say שהכל? Anyway, so it's a longstanding problem that we're not
making the ברכות brachos according to the גמרא Gemara we should be
making. Yes, if we're going to be consistent in כשרות Kashrut law
we should pretty much ignore taste. No, that when we get to
חולין. Chullin. I know we learned חולין. Chullin. All right. I'm being.
Anyway, so just right, just to let you know the jury is
out about a lot of this stuff. אמר רבי חייא בר אשי.
Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi. Past the wide lines. פת צנומה בקערה,
Pas tzenuma b'ke'ara, if you have like sort of dry bread in
a in a plate, מברכין עליו המוציא. m'varchin alav hamotzi. You say
המוציא. Hamotzi Now obviously it's bread, what's the issue? So let's take
a look. ופליגא דרבי חייא, U'pliga d'Rabbi Chiya, argues on רבי חייא.
Rabbi Chiya. דאמר רבי חייא צריך שתכלה ברכה עם הפת. D'amar Rabbi
Chiya tzarich shetichleh bracha im hapas. No, no, no. You don't make
the ברכה, bracha. apparently they would put a slice of bread at
the bottom of the plate and then maybe pour some stew over
it or something. And he says, so you just want this one
slice of bread. This argues on רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya not what
ברכה bracha you make, but on what object you make the ברכה.
bracha You should not make the ברכה bracha on a slice, you
should make the ברכה bracha on the whole loaf. So before we
had prioritizing ברכות Brachos that are more specific, here we have prioritizing
and then there was a question about the foods, is it the
food you want more, is it the food that fills you more?
Here it's a priority about somehow the significance of the food. Is
it a whole loaf of bread or a single or a single
slice? Better to make a ברכה bracha on a whole loaf than
on a single slice and that's where we had the whole loaf
where you had a choice. You could take from you had a
loaf right there and you had a slice in front of you.
And then the question becomes, you know, what happens if because you
say no, I want to finish up the old bread before I
start the new one, right, or what if the slice is something
that's a different type of bread you'd rather have the slice than
the loaf? So that always gets the question about what happens when
you have different factors. Anyway, this argues on רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
who says you always make you have to end your ברכה bracha
with the bread, meaning you say המוציא לחם מן הארץ Hamotzi Lechem
Min Ha'aretz as you're breaking off the piece of bread. But you
start with the whole loaf. מתיב ליה רבא, Masif leh Rava, רבא
Rava said, מאי שנא צנומה דלא משום דכי חלה ברכה אפרוסה חלה?
mai shna tzenuma d'lo mishum d'ki chala bracha a'perusa chala? Why do
you not make it on this slice of bread? Because when the
ברכה bracha. ends it's only a slice, you know, it starts a
slice, it ends a slice. על פת נמי, Al pas nami, if
you make it over the bread which was understood to be as
you're breaking the bread, כי קגמרה אפרוסה גמרה. ki k'gamra a'perusa gamra.
By the time you've finished the ברכה bracha you're over a slice,
it's also a piece. So it started with the loaf but it
ended with a piece. אלא איפוך ל"ט ע"ב. Ela ipuch lamed-tes amud
bais. אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, rather רבא Rava says, מברך
ואחר כך בוצע, m'varech v'achar kach botze'a, which is what we do.
You say המוציא Hamotzi. and then you break off the piece. You
don't break off as you're saying המוציא. Hamotzi, נהרדעי עבדי כרבי חייא.
Nahardei avdi k'Rabbi Chiya. In נהרדעי Nehardea they did like רבי חייא,
Rabbi Chiya, they were breaking it as they were making the ברכה.
bracha, ורבנן עבדי כרבא, v'rabbanan avdi k'Rava, and the rabbis, the rabbinic
students did like רבא, Rava, they first made the full ברכה bracha.
and then they broke off the piece. Is this סוגיא sugya the
reason for the practice? Yes, I'm getting, I'm getting there. אמר רבינא,
Amar Ravina, so רבינא Ravina said, אמרה לי אם, amra li em,
my mother said to me, אבוך, avuch, your father, apparently he had
passed away, עביד כרבי חייא, avid k'Rabbi Chiya, did like רבי חייא,
Rabbi Chiya, דאמר רבי חייא צריך שתכלה ברכה עם הפת. d'amar Rabbi
Chiya tzarich shetichleh bracha im hapas. You end it with the bread,
meaning you're somehow understood to mean you're breaking the bread as you're
saying it. ורבנן עבדי כרבא. V'rabbanan avdi k'Rava. The rabbis did like
רבא. Rava. והלכתא. V'hilchesa. No, see, I don't she might have she
didn't say והלכתא. v'hilchesa. Anyway, there's a general question even if the
גמרא Gemara said והלכתא, v'hilchesa, a lot of the הלכות in ברכות
brachos are גאוני. Geonic. והלכתא כרבא. V'hilchesa k'Rava. We rule like רבא.
Rava. דאמר מברך ואחר כך בוצע. D'amar m'varech v'achar kach botze'a. First
you make it, then you break the bread. So now take a
look at תוספות. Tosafot So he says the first wide I'm sorry
start over from the beginning פירש Peyresh the first תוספות Tosafot שלא
יפריש הפרוסה מן הפת עד אחר ברכה. shelo yafrish haperusa min hapas
ad achar bracha. ויש נוהגים לברך ברכת המוציא קודם שיחתוך כדי שתהא
הפת שלמה בשעת ברכה. v'yesh nohagim l'varech birchas hamotzi kodem sheyachtoch kedei
shetehei hapas shleima b'sha'as bracha. You say the ברכה, bracha המוציא, Hamotzi.
and then you start cutting. ואין v'ein that it takes you so
much time to cut the bread by it'll be like you know
whatever ten seconds half a minute or whatever till you get the
bread in your mouth after you've made the ברכה. bracha Of course
you want to do ומיהו בשבת נכון להחמיר לברך קודם שיחתוך u'mihu
b'shabbos nachon l'hachmir l'vareich kodem sheyachtoch what by שבת shabbos you should
שלא תשמט ידו לפצוע קודם שתכלה הברכה shelo tishmat yado liftzo'a kodem
shetichleh habracha that you know what תוספות is basically suggesting is you
cut halfway you make the ברכה bracha and then you finish cutting
not a scratch like we do that's what he suggests so therefore
you've basically begun cutting but it's still it hasn't been totally separated
and then you finish cutting but he says by שבת shabbos don't
do that because if you cut halfway you might accidentally finish and
then you don't have a שלם shaleim for לחם משנה lechem mishneh
right this is maybe your only whole loaf other whole loaf of
bread so he says well if you did that you have backup
לפצוע קודם שתכלה הברכה liftzo'a kodem shetichleh habracha so אז לא יהיה
לכם משנה. az lo yihyeh lachem mishneh. Okay and then he goes
on. So תוספות says normally you want actually not to be which
is why the מנהג minhag of some people to just tear the
חלה challah apart so you don't have to wait and you get
right into it but it's balancing those issues of not having a
long pause right with the time it takes to do the whole
cut with having a שלם. shaleim. The ראש rosh says that what
would define a cut to the point that it's no longer שלם
shaleim he says that if you כי ki if you picked up
the חלה challah by the piece of bread that's now separating would
the whole חלה challah come with or would it break off and
if the whole חלה challah would come with it's still considered שלם.
shaleim. So the advice is cut a little bit you know make
the ברכה bracha and finish so not a scratch actually begin cutting
but תוספות says on שבת shabbos he's afraid you'll go too far
and you'll ruin the שלם shaleim for שבת shabbos so the scratch
is like a compromise although a lot of people spend so much
time looking for the scratch thing it's counterproductive. Anyway yeah the breakaway
חלות challahs that's yeah those are good מנהגים. minhagim. Okay alright whatever
איתמר itmar let's take a look. So they said הביאו לפניהם פתיתין
ושלמין hevi'u lifneihem pesisin u'shleimin now you have little pieces of bread
and whole loaves it should be obvious what you're going to do
אמר רב הונא amar rav huna מברך על הפתיתין ופוטר את השלמין
mevareich al hapesisin u'poter es hashleimin so that's shocking you make it
on the small pieces and you exempt the big ones which means
it's acceptable not you must but it's acceptable to make on the
small and not on the שלם shaleim you know it's not a
thing to make on a whole loaf as an idea ורבי יוחנן
אמר v'rabbi yochanan amar שלמה מצוה מן המובחר shleima mitzvah min hamuvchar
it's better to make on a שלם shaleim אבל פרוסה של חטין
aval prusa shel chitin now what happens when you cross sort of
you have different preferences being mixed you have פרוסה של חטין prusa
shel chitin you have a slice of wheat bread ושלמה מן השעורין
u'shleima min hase'orin and a whole one of barley so now why
is wheat better there's two reasons one is just it's better it's
a tastier food people don't eat barley bread as much it was
more for animals and number two is חטה chittah comes earlier in
the פסוק pasuk right and תוספות makes a he quotes רש״י rashi
I don't think it's in our רש״י rashi anyway that that's the
key here that if it comes earlier in the פסוק pasuk is
also the reason that it gets an earlier ברכה bracha so which
one wins out so it says there דברי הכל מברך על הפרוסה
divrei hakol mevareich al haprusa there the idea of wheat comes first
you make it on the slice של חטין shel chitin ופוטר את
השלמה u'poter es hashleima and you exempt the whole one של שעורין
shel se'orin that is of barley so here we see at least
when it comes to which one comes first in the פסוק pasuk
that is more important than whole versus not whole it's complicated I
don't want to get into it I mean there's a lot of
תוספות here trying to figure out exactly what the order is I
will tell you that תוספות basically says the order is the following
first you go by specificity of ברכה bracha then you go by
if it's the same ברכה bracha which comes first in the פסוק
pasuk then you go if they're all the same on that then
you go by the whole thing versus the slice and if that's
all equal then you go by which one you want more which
one is of higher quality specificity of ברכה bracha what was your
example of that העץ ha'eitz versus האדמה העץ ha'eitz versus שהכל and
so on even if they're the same ברכה bracha you go by
which one comes first in the פסוק pasuk if they're the same
type of species they're equal in the פסוק pasuk or they're neither
in the פסוק pasuk then you go by whole versus slice and
if that's equal then you go by which you either taste better
or is a higher quality that becomes another question which is you
don't have to eat stuff you're not interested in but let's say
you're interested in eating it later you know you first want to
start with this and eat that that's why the whole thing becomes
a bit of a question you don't have to eat a whole
bread just because to make a ברכה bracha. as opposed to I
just wanted a slice and have a slice there that's the question
if you're only interested in the slice and you didn't want to
start the other loaf of bread right so that might put the
loaf of bread like as irrelevant off the table as it were
a lot of these are you know that's a question right how
do you weigh these types of formal priorities with what with your
interest okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this אמר רב
ירמיה בר אבא כתנאי amar rav yirmeyah bar abba k'tanna'ei this is
based on a debate of תנאים tanna'im which is in a non-ברכות
scenario תורמין בצל קטן שלם אבל לא חצי בצל גדול tormin batzal
katan shaleim aval lo chatzi batzal gadol would you take תרומה terumah
you can choose between a half half of a big onion or
a whole small onion. Which one do you do? So the first
opinion says that you take a small onion. It's better to go
with a whole thing is the way we're reading this than to
go with something bigger and maybe even better because it's bigger, tastes
maybe even a bigger onion tastes better, sweeter. Better to go with
a whole thing. That always is more significant. רבי יהודה אומר לא
כי אלא חצי בצל גדול. Rabbi Yehuda omer lo ki ela chatzi
batzel gadol. No, you go by the half of the big one.
מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? Mai lav beha kamiflagi? It sounds like they're
debating this. דמר סבר חשוב עדיף ומר סבר שלם עדיף. De'mar savar
chashuv adif u'mar savar shalem adif. One says the more important one
is better and the other says the whole one. Now what makes
it more important? We know by the case of the wheat bread
that wheat is more important, it's a higher quality, it's earlier in
the פסוק. pasuk. What makes this more important? So it could just
be that it's more quantity or תוספות says that we're talking about
a big onion and somehow it tasted better than a small onion.
So again, it's not exactly clear what the other criteria is here.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. No, that's not necessarily true.
היכא דאיכא כהן, Heicha de'ika kohen, if there's a כהן kohen around
to give it to, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דחשוב עדיף. kulei alma
lo pligi de'chashuv adif. Then your primary concern has to be an
interesting point, not somehow like ritually, formally which one looks better, but
your concern is the כהן kohen who will receive it. And the
כהן kohen who will receive it would prefer the half of the
big onion, either it's more amount or it tastes better. That has
to override rather than some ritual idea of having something that technically
is like, you know, whole, because the end is to give it
to the כהן. kohen. כי פליגי דליכא כהן. Ki pligi de'leika kohen.
And we're talking about there's no כהן. kohen. You're going to take
תרומה Trumah then, who knows if a כהן kohen will show up
before the thing rots. דתנן, De'tannan, we taught in the משנה: כל
מקום שיש כהן תורם מן היפה. Kol makom she'yesh kohen torem min
hayaffeh. If there's a כהן, kohen, you give from the thing that's
nicer, you know, nicer from the כהן's kohen perspective presumably. וכל מקום
שאין כהן תורם מן המתקיים. V'chol makom she'ein kohen torem min hamitkayem.
If there's no כהן, kohen, you take from things that has better,
that's lasting, that will, you know, that will last longer so that
if the כהן kohen shows up six months from now you'll still
have what to give him. רבי יהודה אומר אין תורם אלא מן
היפה. Rabbi Yehuda omer ein torem ela min hayaffeh. Rabbi Yehuda says
no, even if there's no כהן kohen in front of you, then
you don't focus on the כהן, kohen, you focus on the act
of taking תרומה Trumah and you do it in the sort of
nicer way of taking תרומה Trumah without focusing on the כהן. kohen.
So here the concern is is what? That if the כהן kohen
is here, everybody agrees that the bigger loaf, the bigger onion is
nicer, it's something more desirable and so on. But as we all
know, once you cut fruit or vegetables or whatever, they're going to
rot much sooner. So therefore the question is, do you still focus
on the nicer one which the כהן kohen will like if he
shows up, or do you focus on the one that will last
longer? So therefore it's not really relevant to our case. Now I
told you that the מהר"ם מרוטנבורג throughout all of תוספות is saying,
"play it safe, play it safe." So here the גמרא Gemara, does
that. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק: Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak: ירא
שמים יוצא ידי שניהם. Yere shamayim yotzei yedei shneihem. Somebody who's God-fearing
will satisfy both of these opinions, whether you do the, you know,
the bread, the wheat bread first or the what-do-you-call-it or the barley
bread that's whole. ומנו? U'mannu? Who is this person? מר בריה דרבינא,
Mar brei de'Ravina, it's Mar the son of Ravina. דמר בריה דרבינא
מניח פרוסה בתוך השלמה ובוצע, De'Mar brei de'Ravina maniach prusa betoch hashleima
u'votzea, puts the piece inside of the whole one and he therefore
and he makes המוציא. Hamotzi Now רש"י says it's just big versus
small, the first debate, but that תוספות says is strange because like
there it said maybe you're allowed to make on the pieces but
nobody said like you have to make on the pieces. So תוספות
wants to say this is still the issue we've been talking about,
about where the slice is of higher quality, it's wheat or earlier
in the פסוק, pasuk, and the whole one is of lesser quality
or it's later in the פסוק. pasuk. Which wins out? And therefore
he said, you know, you don't know, you put them together and
it's like you make the ברכה on both of them at the
same time. So this gets to this whole issue of, you know,
play it safe. So now the גמרא says like this. תני תנא
קמיה דרב נחמן. Tani tanna kamei de'Rav Nachman. So a תנא tanna
taught in front of רב נחמן בר יצחק: Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak:
מניח פרוסה בתוך השלמה ובוצע. Maniach prusa betoch hashleima u'votzea. He actually
had this as a ברייתא Braisa that this was the advice of
what you do, whereas רב נחמן Rav Nachman said that no, said
that it was something he saw from רבינא. Ravina. Anyway, ומברך u'mevarech
and then you make the ברכה. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said
to him, מה שמך? Mah shimcha? What's your name? He said to
this תנא tanna who was teaching this ברייתא. Braisa. אמר ליה שלמן.
Amar lei Shalman. My name is Shalman. אמר ליה שלום אתה ושלמה
משנתך. Amar lei Shalom atta u'shleima mishnatecha. You are, you should have
peace and your teaching is peace, ששמת שלום בין התלמידים. she'samta shalom
bein hatalmidim. You made peace between the תלמידים, talmidim, you've reconciled. Of
course there's a play on words here because it's the שלם, shalem,
you know, you put the piece amongst the, you know, the פרוסה
prusa in the שלם. shalem. So it's sort of, and there's this
nice idea about the whole piece bringing everything together. Since you're focusing
on the שלם, shalem, it brings it all together and therefore you
have made peace. From a literary point of view, it's not believable
that this is an authentic ברייתא Braisa because you have the whole
pun, the whole thing is a pun reinforcing the opinion. And רב
נחמן בר יצחק... Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak... quoted it, but I will
say on the flip that that you do have very often in
the בבלי *Bavli* ברייתות *braitot* that don't appear in the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*
but that are word for word Amoraic statements. Like very often you'll
have a ברייתא *braita* which is like אמר רבא *Amar Rava* A,
B, C, D, E, F. תניא נמי הכי *Tanya nami hachi* A,
B, C, D, E, F. And when you have that, it very
it like is almost never in the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*. And it seems
that in the in the בבלי *Bavli* they would sometimes confuse Amoraic
statements with ברייתות *braitot* and things that had been Amoraic statements would
be taught as ברייתות *braitot*. At least that's a way of explaining
that phenomenon. So I don't know if this is impossible, this actually
is a phenomenon that happens that something but you know but nevertheless
it you know I the point is taken regardless. It's also nice
in a contrast to what we read on עמוד א *amud aleph*
where he was upset and you know he was the type of
critical response here he gave him a very nice response and you
know at a very you know because teaching that he liked. And
he also mentions the name of a תנא *tanna* you know. Well
that's true. Okay that's true. אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Papa* now
we get to פסח *Pesach*. הכל מודים בפסח *Hakol modim bePesach* everybody
remembers פסח *Pesach* שמניח פרוסה בתוך שלמה *shemaniach prusa betoch shlema* you
put the piece inside of the whole one ובוצע *uvotze'a* and you
make the ברכה *bracha*. They were probably dealing with by the way
פיתה *pita* and not our flat you know type of soft מצות
*matzot* so you can put it inside as opposed to we just
put them like together. You know but that's why we hold both
up and we say המוציא Hamotzi. *Hamotzi* and then we you know
and then we drop one and we say על אכילת מצה *al
achilat matzah*. So well talk about that in a minute let's finish
the גמרא *Gemara* on this. אמר ליה Amar lei, מאי טעמא *Amar
lei mai ta'ama* what's the reason? לחם עוני כתיב *Lechem oni ktiv*
it's poor person's bread and poor person is we're supposed to have
a פרוסה *prusa* a half of a piece. So there's a whole
interesting debate in the פוסקים *poskim* about how to deal with the
מצה *matzah* on פסח *Pesach*. First of all, do you hold all
three or do you just hold two? Some say that because by
פסח *Pesach* there's an idea of לחם עוני *lechem oni* then then
the issue is do you have two שלמים *shlemim* for לחם משנה
Lechem Mishneh *lechem mishneh*? That's the question. So that's why we hold
the bottom one as well to get two full loaves for לחם
משנה Lechem Mishneh, *lechem mishneh*. But some ראשונים *rishonim* say you don't
need to worry about a full loaf. The part the half loaf
is so the you know is the broken מצה *matzah* is considered
to be a loaf for these purposes. That's the status of a
loaf on פסח *Pesach* night. It's לחם עוני *lechem oni*. It's a
broken loaf. So there's one question: do you hold three מצות *matzot*
to begin with or two? Now the general מנהג minhag *minhag* at
least amongst אשכנזים *Ashkenazim* I don't know about ספרדים *Sefardim* is you
first hold three and you make המוציא Hamotzi, *Hamotzi* so you're making
it on two on two whole loaves. Then you drop and then
you make על אכילת מצה *al achilat matzah* and you're supposed to
actually be thinking about that ברכה *bracha* on the middle one because
since the middle broken one is the לחם עוני *lechem oni* that's
the one that we sort of you know prioritize in terms of
its status of that's the מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* of מצות *matzot* being
done on the middle obviously you're יצא *yotzei* the מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*
on any but that's the one we sort of hone in on.
תוספות *Tosafot* also leads to questions about making multiple ברכות *brachot* on
the same object. Is it considered like piling up מצוות *mitzvot* which
you're not supposed to do? And maybe that's why when we're thinking
about המוציא Hamotzi *Hamotzi* we're thinking about the top one and when
we say על אכילת מצה *al achilat matzah* we're thinking about the
middle. In the end תוספות *Tosafot* says it's not really a concern
that ברכת הנהנין *birchat hanehenin* is not piling up מצוות *mitzvot*. You
know we make בורא פרי הגפן *borei pri hagafen* and we also
make all the ברכות *brachot* of קידוש *Kiddush* on the wine. So
what's the מנהג *minhag* of ספרדים *Sefardim* Rav? The רמב"ם *Rambam* is
really clear that you make המוציא *Hamotzi* on the broken piece. Right.
But do they so the ספרדים *Sefardim* hold all three first? I
don't know what widespread practice but there's a strong there's a strong
practice not to start with all three but to have the interesting
but I don't know that every ספרדי *Sefardi* community holds. Right right.
Okay. So let's now see how the גמרא *Gemara* wraps whatever or
moves on with this. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. אמר
רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi, *Amar Rav Ashi* חזינא ליה לרב כהנא
Chazina lei l'Rav Kahana, *chazina lei leRav Kahana* I saw Rav Kahana
דנקיט תרתי ובצע חדא d'nakit tartei u'vatza chada. *denakit tarti uvatza chada*.
Did I skip a line? I'm sorry time out. אמר רב אבא
*Amar Rav Abba* ובשבת *uvShabbat* חייב אדם לבצוע על שתי ככרות *chayav
adam livtzo'a al shtei kikarot*. By שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* you have to
have two loaves of bread. Look at that right there it's in
this גמרא *Gemara*. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*? דכתיב *dechtiv* מאי טעמא *mai
ta'ama* לחם משנה כתיב *lechem mishneh ktiv*. It says לחם משנה *lechem
mishneh* they got double and therefore we have double which by the
way the simple reading of this is not on יום טוב *Yom
Tov*. That you don't need שתי לחם *shtei lechem* on יום טוב
*Yom Tov*. Okay and there was a you know on פסח *Pesach*
this is what you do. שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat* there you need שתי
לחם *shtei lechem*. There's a whole debate in the ראשונים *rishonim* whether
you need it. Partly it's a debate about whether the מן Man,
*man* double מן Man *man* fell ערב יום טוב *erev Yom Tov*.
It's a little funny since יום טוב *Yom Tov* you're allowed to
do things relating to food and obviously we know it's our מנהג
*minhag* that שתי לחם *shtei lechem* on יום טוב *Yom Tov* but
it's a serious מחלוקת *machloket*. This גמרא *Gemara* makes it sound pretty
much like it's only on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*. Which is which therefore
if it's only on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* why did it say you
have the broken and the whole on פסח *Pesach*? Not to do
לחם משנה *lechem mishneh* but because of this issue about the importance
of make a ברכה *bracha* on a whole loaf but on the
other hand there's an importance to a half loaf on פסח *Pesach*
and you therefore you have them both. I should mention by the
way that the הלכה halacha, *halacha* very important הלכה halacha. *halacha* that
people don't know, the הלכה *halacha* of שלמים *shlemim* is certainly a
requirement for לחם משנה *lechem mishneh* but it's not a בדיעבד *bedi'avad*
requirement. If you don't have a whole loaf of bread you would
still two use two slices and make לחם משנה *lechem mishneh* in
order for you know because you can get לחם משנה *lechem mishneh*
without a whole loaf. Now here's an interesting question a question for
you to do at home. Question for the student, which is, what
if you have one whole loaf and it's שבת, and that's the
only thing you have? Do you make a המוציא on the whole
loaf, or do you break it in half so that you have
לחם משנה out of two half loaves? So I'll let you do
that for a homework assignment. Okay, so now the גמרא says like
this. Okay, אמר רב אשי, Rav Ashi, חזינא ליה לרב כהנא, said
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, I've seen רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, דנקיט תרתי
ובצע חדא. He held two loaves on שבת and he broke one
loaf. You don't have to break both, even though he had a
לחם משנה, it's enough to actually eat from one, you don't have
to eat from both, which we know we do. רב זירא Rav
Zeira הוי בצע אכולה שירותא. hava batza akulei sheruta. רב זירא Rav
Zeira when he would take a chunk of bread for שבת, it
would be a huge chunk, enough to last him the whole meal.
אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi, so רבינא
Ravina said to רב אשי, והא קמתחזי כרעבתנותא? v'ha kamitchazi k'ra'avtanusa? It
looks like, you know, like a guy starving, you know, there's gotta
be an adjective for this, what is it? Anyway, but anyway, it's
inappropriate, you know, a huge chunk of bread, like the other guy
looks like you never had meat in your whole life. אמר ליה,
כיון דכל יומא לא קעביד הכי, keivan d'chol yoma lo ka'avid hachi,
normally he doesn't do that, והאידנא קעביד ליה, v'idna ka'avid lei, and
now he's doing it, לא מתחזי כרעבתנותא. lo mitchazi k'ra'avtanusa. It does
not look like, you know, he's doing it just because he has
no manners. Now it's not exactly clear why is he doing it.
Is there an idea you should have a full amount for your
meal, then why doesn't he do it the rest of the week?
Somehow there's probably something that it's because it's the loaves used for
שבת, it was, you know, gave some status. But again, it's funny,
it doesn't even spell out exactly what was motivating that. רב אמי
ורב אסי, Rav Ami v'Rav Assi, there are some opinions that say
that when you, you should cut very thick slices so that it's
enough for the person for ממש mamash the meal. So it is
right, but then it's not a specific שבת הלכה, it's a general
הלכה. But in context here in the סוגיא, sugya, it's connected to
the מן, Man, that is to say the מן fed for the
entire... oh, that's a nice point! So you're maintaining that the idea
of the מן, that's a very nice point. Okay, thank you, that's
a very nice point. רב אמי ורב אסי כי הוי מסרמי להו
ריפתא דעירובא, Rav Ami v'Rav Assi ki hava misrami lehu rifta d'eruva,
when they had bread from that was used for an עירוב, eruv,
you know, an עירוב חצירות, eruv chatzeiros, or we would use have
the food left over from עירוב תבשילין, eruv tavshilin, מברכין עליה המוציא
לחם מן הארץ, mevarchin aleha Hamotzi Lechem Min Ha'aretz, they'd make a
point of eating it and saying a המוציא. Now obviously you have
to say המוציא, but it seems like the point is, is that
they wouldn't give it to somebody else, they made a point of
eating it. אמרי הואיל ואיתעביד בה מצוה חדא, Amri ho'il v'is'avid bah
mitzvah chada, since it was used for one מצוה, נעביד בה מצוה
אחריתי, na'avid bah mitzvah achriti, let's do another מצוה, let's make המוציא
on it, let's eat it. And there actually is a מנהג of
trying to make sure, you know, that you eat the bread, the
food for, that you use for עירוב חצירות, eruv chatzeiros, for עירוב
תחומין... eruv techumin... not תחומין, techumin, excuse me, תבשילין. tavshilin. Thank you,
עירוב תבשילין. eruv tavshilin. Right. Because of this גמרא, which we continue
now.